Guide to the Silas Gilbert Patterson Papers 1692-1913 MS 024 MS 024 MS 024
Cornwall Historical Society
Silas Gilbert Patterson Papers
1692-1913
Cornwall Historical Society
Patterson, Silas Gilbert
MS 024
1 linear feet (2 boxes)
Silas Gilbert Patterson was born in Cornwall in 1838. A land surveyor by trade, Patterson resided in Cornwall Bridge and operated the Bonney Farm.
Provenance
The collection was given to the Cornwall Historical Society in 1986 by the Goshen Historical Society, after they received them from a Patterson descendant living in Torrington, Connecticut.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Silas Gilbert Patterson was born in Cornwall in 1838. A land surveyor by trade, Patterson resided in Cornwall Bridge and operated the Bonney Farm. The papers in the S. G. Patterson Collection mainly relate to his interest in genealogy. Patterson collected information on families that he was descended from personally, as well as other local Cornwall families that piqued his interest.
Sources:
Scope and Content Note
The collection is contained in two archival boxes. The first series consists of letters written to and from S. G. Patterson. Most of these letters concern genealogical questions, although several personal letters deal with issues such as business at the Bonney Farm, family news, and Patterson’s efforts to help a friend reconnect with relatives in Ireland.
The second series consists mainly of genealogical and historical documents collected by S. G. Patterson. Patterson had a particular interest in the Hart family and collected dozens of deeds relating to them. The Hart deeds detail the family’s movement from Farmington, Connecticut westward to newly laid-out townships like Cornwall and Canaan, Connecticut as well as New Marlborough and Tyringham, Massachusetts. The rest of the documents are an assortment of personal items and genealogical and historical research.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Correspondence
Hart Materials
Personal Papers
Historical and Genealogical Materials
Miscellaneous Materials
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Cornwall (Conn.); Correspondence; Patterson, Silas Gilbert; Patterson, Silas Gilbert; Cornwall Historical Society
- Correspondence
  - Bonney Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with E. G. Patterson, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 2-Jan)
    - Correspondence with Henry B. Patterson, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with Lizzie Waite, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Calhoun Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with J. E. Calhoun, 1892-1895 (Box 1, Folder 6-May)
  - Everest Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with W. H. Everest, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 8-Jul)
  - Gilbert Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with H. W. Carter, 1905-1907 (Box 1, Folder 12-Sep)
    - Correspondence with Mrs. H. W. Carter, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence with Caroline Derwechter, 1907-1912 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    - Correspondence with Alice Gilbert, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence with H. M. Gilbert, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Correspondence with J. R. Gilbert, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence with W. H. Gilbert, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence with A. B. Hodge, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence with Elma G. Irish, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - Correspondence with M. G. Miner, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
    - Correspondence with E. G. Patterson, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence with A. H. Ward, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hopkins Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with G. C. Harrison, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence with G. C. Hopkins, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence with Timothy Hopkins, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence with Cynthia R. H. Monroe, 1908-1912 (Box 1, Folder 33-35)
    - Correspondence with E. H. Myers, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - Correspondence with E. N. Shepard, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Patterson Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with D. M. Chalker, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence with S. A. Chalker, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence with O. Dinwiddle, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence with W. Downing, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence with C. N. Downs, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence with T. S. Gold, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence with L. M. Lemmon, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
    - Correspondence with Mrs. G. L. Moore, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence with E. G. Patterson, 1890-1903 (Box 1, Folder 48-58)
    - Correspondence with George S. Patterson, 1895-1898 (Box 1, Folder 59-61)
    - Correspondence with Mary J. Patterson, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Correspondence with Jerome J. Patterson, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Correspondence with Joseph Patterson, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Correspondence with G. D. Seymour, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Sackett Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with Phebe Comstock, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Correspondence with C. H. Weygant, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Sturtevant Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with H. W. Carter, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Correspondence with Mrs. J. S. Comstock, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Correspondence with Mary E. Mason, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Correspondence with S. G. Patterson, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Correspondence with W. H. Sturtevant, 1902-1910 (Box 1, Folder 72-74)
  - Taylor Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with E. W. Brown, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 75-76)
  - Twiss Genealogical Correspondence
    - Correspondence with J. Huntington, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Correspondence with J. Twiss, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Isolated Genealogical Queries
    - Inquiry regarding the Bradford family, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Inquiry regarding the Carter family, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Inquiry regarding the Fuller family, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Inquiry regarding the Harrison family, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Inquiry regarding the Nye family, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Inquiry regarding the Sherwood family, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Inquiry regarding the Starr family, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Inquiry regarding the Swan family, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Correspondence with Bonney and Patterson family members regarding business at the Bonney Farm, 1876-1881 (Box 1, Folder 87-89)
    - Letter from N. L. Bonney, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Note from R. B. Eaphy, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Correspondence regarding the heirs of Seth, Amy, and Marietta Pierce, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 92-93)
    - Letter from Henry Patterson, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Correspondence regarding Meaghur family members in Ireland, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 95-96)
    - Letter and attached newspaper article by S. G. Patterson from A. P. Smith, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Assortment of empty envelopes, undated (Box 1, Folder 98)
- Hart Materials
  - Index to Hart property transactions, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - John Hart deeds, 1727-1764 (Box 2, Folder 14-Feb)
  - Appointment of Seth Pierce as executor of John Hart’s estate, 1779 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Nathan Hart deed from Joel Millard, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rufus Hart deeds with Seth Pierce, 1794-1798 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Silas Hart deeds with Seth and Amy Pierce, 1782-1799 (Box 2, Folder 20-24)
  - Solomon Hart deeds, 1759-1796 (Box 2, Folder 25-33)
  - Inventory of Solomon Hart estate, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Thomas Hart deed to Seth Pierce, 1784 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Titus Hart deed from Phineas Hart, 1801 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Titus Hart probate information, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Personal Papers
  - Tax notice, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bank records with The Iron Bank of Fall’s Village and First National Bank of New Milford, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Fire insurance policy on the Bonney Farm, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Composition book listing meteorological data, business dealings with the Cornwall Bridge Iron Co., and personal genealogical information, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Milk bill from Hart Co., undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Empty canvas pouch, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Historical and Genealogical Materials
  - Ebenezer Birdseye deed to Seth Pierce, 1796 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - E. W. Brown raffle ticket, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Carter family notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Youngs Eliot militia appointment, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Will of Jacob Everest (copy), 692 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Everest genealogy, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Lewey A. B. Griswold obituary, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - List of polls and ratable estate, Cornwall, 1802 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Fuller family tree, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Genealogical notes on the Gilbert family, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - “Genealogical” section of the Boston Evening Transcript, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Hopkins family tree, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Notes on Hopkins-Sturtevant family, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Samuel A. Judson petition to Litchfield Superior Court, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Patrick McGowan indenture to Riley Rexford, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Matthew Millard deed to Joseph Pangborn, 1746 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Judd Murphy summons, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Andrew Patterson information, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Genealogy of the Patterson family, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - History of the Patterson family, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Memoranda from Elnathan Patterson’s account book, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Notes on descendants of Sherman and Huldah Patterson, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Revolutionary War record of Sherman Patterson, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Biographical information on Silas Patterson, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Patterson vital records, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Russell Pratt and Stephen Foster petition to Litchfield Superior Court, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Property map, North Cornwall, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Thomas Robbins deed to Elijah Griswould, 1765 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - “Sackett Family in America,” by C. H. Weygant, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Jacob Scoville summons, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Genealogical notes on Sherman family, undated (Box 2, Folder 74-75)
  - Survey of land on Canaan Mountain, 1781 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Notes on the Taylor family, undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Letter from George Wheaton to James Wadsworth, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - George Wheaton deed to Daniel B. Phillips, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Charles Whittesey letter from his son, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Complaint of assault involving Henry Willis, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 81)
- Miscellaneous Materials
  - Folder with notes on collection’s provenance from Goshen Historical Society, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 83)